<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf8'?>
<SHOPITEM>
<ITEM_ID>533861</ITEM_ID>
<PRODUCTNAME>
Effect of specific hydrocolloids and hydrocolloid blends on gluten-free bread quality
</PRODUCTNAME>
<PRODUCT>
Effect of specific hydrocolloids and hydrocolloid blends on gluten-free bread quality
</PRODUCT>
<EAN>9788074547843</EAN>
<ISBN>978-80-7454-784-3</ISBN>
<PRICE_VAT>0</PRICE_VAT>
<DESCRIPTION>

Increasing demand of gluten-free breads leads to widespread researches to offer quality goods. Gluten-free flours (amaranth, buckwheat, chickpea, millet, quinoa and rice) themselves, in two-component blend (50% rice flour and 50% amaranth, buckwheat, chickpea, millet or quinoa flour) and in three-component blend (60% rice flour, 20% amaranth flour and 20% buckwheat flour etc.) were submitted to the baking test. Satisfactory results presented the combination of buckwheat and rice flour in portion of 50% buckwheat and 50% rice flour, thus baking test of the blends from buckwheat 10% and rice 90% to buckwheat 90% and rice 10% was conducted and the sample buckwheat 40% and rice 60% evaluated as the best sample with 1.30 cm3 g -1 specific volume, hardness of 17.1 N and any negative effect on sensory properties. To improve the overall bread quality, eight hydrocolloids (agar, carob bean gum, gelatine, κ-carrageenan, sodium alginate, sodium carboxymethyl cellulose, tragacanth and xanthan gum) themselves and in two-component blend were applied to the rice flour in 0.5 and 1.0% portion to flour weight and submitted to the baking test including hardness and moisture content 24 and 72 hours after baking. The best results reached the rice samples in combination with agar-cellulose 0.5%, alginate-cellulose 0.5%, alginatexanthan gum 1.0%, carob gum-cellulose 0.5%, carrageenan-gelatine 0.5%, cellulose-gelatine 1.0% and gelatine-tragacanth 0.5%. The blends were then applied into the sample of 40% buckwheat flour and 60% rice flour (BR 4060) and baking test evaluated. The hydrocolloid blends improved loaf specific volume from 1.30 cm3 g -1 to 1.85 cm3 g -1 (BR 4060-agar-cellulose 0.5%), improved dough and bread yield, did not significantly affect baking loss and moisture content 24 and 72 h after baking but deteriorated hardness 24 and 72 h after baking (except for BR-alginate-cellulose 0.5%) compared to the rice and BR 4060 samples.

</DESCRIPTION>
<CATEGORYTEXT>Tištěné knihy | Ostatní a nezařazené</CATEGORYTEXT>
<URL>
https://www.sckn.cz/effect-of-specific-hydrocolloids-and-hydrocolloid-blends-on-gluten-free-bread-quality-pn-533-861/
</URL>
<PARAM>
<PARAM_NAME>Počet stran</PARAM_NAME>
<VAL>46</VAL>
</PARAM>
<PARAM>
<PARAM_NAME>Vazba</PARAM_NAME>
<VAL>e-kniha - pdf</VAL>
</PARAM>
<PARAM>
<PARAM_NAME>Jazyk</PARAM_NAME>
<VAL>anglický</VAL>
</PARAM>
<PARAM>
<PARAM_NAME>Datum vydání</PARAM_NAME>
<VAL>06. 11. 2018</VAL>
</PARAM>
<PARAM>
<PARAM_NAME>Pořadí vydání</PARAM_NAME>
<VAL>První</VAL>
</PARAM>
<CONTRIBUTOR>
<ROLE>Autor</ROLE>
<NAME>Petra</NAME>
<SURNAME>Dvořáková</SURNAME>
</CONTRIBUTOR>
<THEMATIC_GROUP>5 - Technické vědy</THEMATIC_GROUP>
</SHOPITEM>
